Finding Aid for Paralyzed Veterans of America, Michigan Chapter, Records, 1964-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paralyzed Veterans of America, Michigan Chapter, Records 1964-2004 1990-1994
Paralyzed Veterans of America. Michigan Chapter.
0045 Be.2 2
Records of the Paralyzed Veterans of America, Michigan Chapter (MPVA). Includes annual reports, meeting agenda and minutes from the Board of Directors, correspondence files of the main office and executives, information about events sponsored by the MPVA, and a series of topical files.
3.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Paralyzed Veterans of America, Michigan Chapter (donor no. 8916 ) in 2000 and 2006.
The record group is open to research.
The Paralyzed Veterans of America (PVA) is a congressionally chartered veterans service organization dedicated to meeting the needs and interests of men and women who both served in the United States armed forces, and who have a spinal cord injury or disease. The PVA Michigan Chapter ("MPVA") was founded in 1961 with twelve charter members, and has since grown into a statewide non-profit organization that serves thousands of veterans annually.
Over its first 45 years of existence, MPVA's Government Relations and Advocacy Program has been instrumental in the passage and enforcement of a number of State and Federal laws that defend the civil rights of people with disabilities. In particular, MPVA has a long history of advocating for barrier-free design, and its records from the early 1990s evidence the active role the organization took in promoting understanding and enforcement of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990.
Current MPVA programs include counseling on veterans' benefits, sponsoring wheelchair sports and recreation, promoting spinal cord injury research, coordinating equipment donation, advocating for the legal and civil rights of veterans with disabilities, referral services, and providing disability-related literature, including The Pump Guide, an online directory of Michigan gas stations that will pump gas at the self-serve price for persons with disabilities.
Sources:
Further information about the organization will be found in a self-published booklet Paralyzed Veterans of America Michigan Chapter Twenty Fifth Anniversary 1961-1986 located with the organization's records. The researcher should also consult the organization's website: http://comnet.org/mpva/
The Paralyzed Veterans of America, Michigan Chapter ("MPVA") records, 1964-2004 comprises five series: Annual Reports, Board of Directors, Correspondence, Events, and Topical Files.
The newsletter of the organization Rollin' Times has been separately cataloged.
Subjects:
Paralyzed Veterans of America. Michigan Chapter.; Paralytics--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Disabled veterans--Michigan--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Paralyzed Veterans of America--History.; Paralytics--Michigan.; Disabled veterans--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Annual Reports
  Annual Reports contains the final printed versions of the MPVA's annual reports from 1964 to 1965 and 1974 to 2000, including the 25th anniversary special publication from 1986. It also contains prints of the snapshot photographs used in the 2001 annual report.
  - 1964-1965, 1974-2000, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs used in 2001 Annual Report (Box 1)
- Board of Directors
  Board of Directors comprises two agendas, minutes, and miscellaneous documents handed out at meetings from 1982 to 1999 and copies of all motions considered at meetings between 1991 and 1999.
  - Minutes, agenda, etc. 1982-1999, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Motions by date 1991-1999, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The third series, Correspondence, is the largest. It comprises a union of several different correspondence files maintained by various people within the organization between 1988 and 1994. The files in this series have generally been maintained intact, as they were when they were received by the archives, but have been organized by type of file and date. The series include files titled Carbon Copy Correspondence, Deputy Executive Director, Executive Director, General Correspondence, Memoranda, Secretary, State / National Coordination, and Topical Correspondence Files. Also in this series is a Correspondence Log from 1993. The State/National Coordination subseries is of particular interest, as it contains correspondence with Michigan and United States lawmakers on a variety of issues.
  - Carbon copy correspondence 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Carbon copy correspondence 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence log 1993 (Box 2)
  - Deputy Executive Director
    - General 1991-1992, 1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Incoming 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Executive Director
    - Incoming 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - General 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence
    - Incoming 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing 1991-1993, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Memoranda 1991-1994, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Secretary 1994 (Box 3)
  - State / National Coordination
    - General 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Incoming 1991-1994, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Outgoing 1991-1994, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Topical Correspondence Files
    - Americans with Disabilities Act 1994 (Box 3)
    - Association of Chapter Executive Directors 1994 (Box 3)
    - Computer grant 1993 (Box 3)
    - Fund raising (Benefit Systems) 1994 (Box 3)
    - Professional football teams 1992 (Box 3)
    - Radio program 1991-1992 (Box 3)
- Events
  Events documents various annual and occasional events held by MPVA for its members and their families.
  - Awareness Day banquet 1992 (Box 3)
  - Installation of Officers and Awards Banquet 1984-1998, 2002, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Chapter picnic 1996-1998 (Box 3)
  - Holiday parties 1991-2001 (Box 3)
  - Novi charity auction 1999-2001 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series comprises files maintained by various individuals within the organization regarding particular issues. A number of these files came from the Deputy Executive Director's office, while others appear to have been maintained elsewhere. These files provide insight into the types of issues in which MPVA took an active role, particularly during the early 1990s.
  - Access to the skies 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - Auxiliary, no date (Box 4)
  - Barrier-free design 1986-1990 (Box 4)
  - City of Detroit 1990 (Box 4)
  - Directors' obituaries and biographies (Box 4)
  - Engler Interview 1990 (Box 4)
  - Handicap Parking 1990 (Box 4)
  - Health care 1990 (Box 4)
  - Investing in Abilities Week 1990 (Box 4)
  - Jury selection 1990 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Spinal Cord Injury Survey 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Press releases 1989 (Box 4)
  - Proclamations and recognitions 1976-2004 (Box 4)
    (plus one oversize folder)
  - Publications Ordered 1992-1994 (Box 4)
  - Statement on House Bill 4764 1989 (Box 4)
  - Testimony before Senate Appropriations Subcommittee 1988 (Box 4)
  - Videocassette: History of PVA: American Heros (Box 4)
  - "What We Do" undated (Box 4)